Hi. Now that you know
the most accurate theory
...of how electrons came to life,
...let's get into electronics,
...but not quite yet.
I can't just tell you what
the voltage and current are.
The video would be too shor-
You won't quite grasp the meaning!
So when scientists were
discovering electricity,
...they already knew mechanics by heart.
And that's how they were
quantifying electronics.
Mechanical science is the first thing
...any creator is exposed to right away.
Although our bodies are advanced in
...mechanics, electronics,
...chemistry, and computer science,
...it's well beyond our understanding.
All we can really learn right away
...is mechanical science.
Picking things up,
making tools, and such.
No matter if you're
tiny crabs or humans.
So let's learn some
basic mechanical physics.
And what's physics without mentioning
...one of the greatest men
the world has ever known,
He was an all-round scientist
...with his own discoveries
and inventions,
...but his greatest discovery was:
...one of the greatest scientists ever!
Halley talked to the super-introvert
Newton and realized that
...Newton had years of
unpublished discoveries.
Newton already knew that
...the gravitational
force (F) between two masses
...was proportional to
...the product of their masses (M1, M2)
...divided by the square (²)
of their distance (r).
Halley made Newton write his knowledge,
...and published them for
Newton at his own expense.
He gave Newton and his science
the recognition it deserved,
...and this helped make
a big leap in science!
Halley was a great man.
He showed us that you don't
need to be great at something
...to make a big difference.
All you need is to find brilliant
minds without discrimination
...and give them the
ground they need to grow,
...and for that I salute thee!
In his book,
...Newton provided his
three famous laws of motion,
...and the second one states that
...the sum of all forces on an object
...is equal to its mass
times acceleration.
And for that,
...was picked as the unit
of force in his honour.
Later on,
...the great inventor of steam engine,
...developed the:
Every horsepower
...is basically the amount of weight
...a typical horse can pull up
...by one meter every second,
...which is around 75 kilograms
for metric horsepower.
That way, he could compare the
strength of his steam engines
...with the equivalent of horses.
Then
...came along and then said,
"Let's do it properly."
Horses are kind of random,
...and horsepower really only
works for Earth's gravity.
On the moon, horses can pull a house.
The work (W) done on an object
...would be equal to the
force (F) applied to it
(which is mass (M)
times acceleration (a))
...times the length (ℓ) of distance
that object travels under that force.
The work would be the
energy spent by that force
...to move a mass by a given distance.
We need a unit for this.
'Joules'!
Then Joule said,
"Now that we have a nice way
to calculate work or energy,"
"...let's divide it by the amount of
time (t) the energy was spent,"
"...and we will have the
work done in one second,"
"...which is the power (P)."
So if a certain amount of
energy is spent in less time,
...it has a greater punch.
And in honour of James Watt,
...the unit of power
...shall be known as Watts!
"I..."
"...have..."
"...the power!"
And then people became
interested in electricity.
They had already seen
thunder and electric eel,
...and knew that you can make
this magic attractive force
...by rubbing amber against fur.
These are just some pieces of napkin
...and a plastic ruler
...rubbed against animal fur.
But nobody cared
...until later in 16th century,
...the cool boy
...did some study on this
new force and called it:
...in Latin for:
...which later became 'electricity'.
Also, a century and a half later,
...proposed and allegedly performed
...his famous kite experiment.
Well, don't do it at home.
You can't do it at home.
Just don't do it.
Ben's proposed lightning rod experiment
...killed
...back in 1753,
...so I make Benjamin Franklin
...the honorary
...board member. [applause]
Then
...came along and said,
"Well, obviously there is something"
"...flowing inside a
conductive medium like a fluid."
"Let's call that:"
"...shown with a 'q',"
"...with the unit of"
(you guessed it)
Coulomb did an interesting experiment
...to measure the force
between two charged balls.
See, for example,
...if I put some known
charge on my ruler
...and bring it close to my pendulum,
...which is made of a ping-pong ball,
...it will attract the ball.
If I know the weight of the ball
...and how much it moved,
...I can calculate the force imposed
on it by the electric charge.
Coulomb did a similar thing
with two charged balls
...one of which was twisting
a spring-like string.
From that experiment,
...he inferred the Coulomb's law,
...which states that the electric
force (F) between two static charges
...is proportional to the
product of their charges (q₁, q₂)
...divided by the square (²)
of their distance (r).
...which is very similar to
Newton's law of gravity.
Later,
...a teacher and scientist,
...did a bunch of experiments
and realized that
...if we pass electricity
between two adjacent wires,
...they imposed a force on each other
...like this:
The electric current,
which in this case
...goes in the same direction,
...resolves in the wires
attracting each other.
Oh [REDACTED], too much current.
So, the unit of current is named:
...in honour of his research,
...and is shown with the capital 'I'.
The definition of current is,
...if we have two very thin,
parallel, and infinite wires
...one meter apart,
...1 amp is the amount of
current through these wires
...that generate:
...Newtons of force
...per every meter of wire.
Very small force.
I was hoping for a better definition,
...but whatever.
Understanding electric current is easy.
Imagine a water hose,
...and you could measure
the flow based on
...the amount of mass passing
a point in the hose per second,
...like 1 kilogram per second.
2 kilograms per second
would be more current.
We can do the same thing
for electric current,
...except here, mass or
volume don't matter.
Electricity can move
with tiny electrons
...or large ion particles
...in solids, liquids, or gases.
What's important is that
...it's the electric charge that
does the electrical dirty work.
So the electric charge (q) in coulombs
...passing through a
conductor every second (t)
...is equal to the
electric current (I).
And therefore,
1 coulomb is defined as
...the amount of charge that
...1 amp of current can
carry every second.
Of course, back then,
they didn't know that
...it is the electron
passing through the wire.
All they saw was that the electricity
...flows between opposing charges.
So they called the charge
on one side 'positive',
...and on the other side 'negative',
...and said the current flows
from positive to negative.
Later, based on this definition,
...we figured that the
electrons are actually negative
...and move reverse of
the defined current flow.
But that didn't affect the
science and calculations.
And, in fact, sometimes
we can argue that
...it's the positive ions
that carry the charges,
...so we're stuck with
the original definition.
In the meantime,
...came along.
He made the first battery, called
...'voltaic pile',
...which of course was well
after the Baghdad battery,
...made by aliens to
power pyramids. [sarcasm]
His battery was a source
of electrical energy.
If you connected a circuit across it,
...it would provide
the energy that would
...push the current
through the circuit.
Back to mechanics.
If I hold a mass above a surface,
...the force (F) applied
to it is equal to
...its mass (m) times the
gravitational acceleration of Earth (g).
If I let go it from the height (h),
...it releases an energy equal to
...the force (F) times
distance (in this case, h)
...or mgh.
But if I don't let go,
...this mass has the potential
...to release that much energy.
Similarly,
...if we have two charged balls
like in Coulomb's setup,
We know how much force is between them
...from Coulomb's law.
And knowing their distance,
...we know the total
electric potential energy
...they would release if let go.
Now, the interesting thing is that
...the total energy doesn't
affect the current.
It's like you're holding 1 kilogram
of water at a certain height,
...or a huge ocean of water
at the same height,
...and all the water has to
go through a single pipe.
The water would still have to
go down 1 kilogram at a time,
...and the current
would be dependent on
...the gravitational acceleration
...and the height that the 1 kilogram
has to go down through.
...which is basically the
total potential energy,
...mgh,
...divided by mass (m),
(or just gh)
...which is called their specific energy.
Same thing with electronics.
The electric current is not
dependent on the total energy,
...but the available
energy per unit charge
...or joules per coulomb.
And the unit for this,
...in honour of
...Alessandro Giuseppe Antonio Anastasio
...Volta
...is named:
Voltage is also known as:
...and the voltage difference
between any two points in space
...is the difference between
their electric potentials.
After all is said and done,
...I just want you to remember these:
Voltage is the amount
of energy (in joules)
...available to move
one coulomb of charge.
And current is the amount
of charge (in coulombs)
...passing in one second.
And when the voltage value of one point
...is higher than the other point,
...and there is a
conductive path between them,
...the positive current (I)
...runs from the higher
voltage to the lower.
That's all.
Remember these,
...and I'll see you next time,
But
...man!
He wrapped the whole thing in math!
And where were women
...when all these great men
were shaping the world?
They were busy being
discriminated against,
...fighting to get their basic rights!
They were not even allowed
the proper education,
...forced into doing what
'a woman should do'.
Do you remember I was talking about
...finding brilliant minds
without discrimination?
The world would be
a much better place!
We would be way further ahead
without discrimination.
Don't do it at home.
♫